Welcome back. How did you go making your
plate? Hope you all attempted it. If you
didn't or you got stuck, don't worry
because I'm going to show you how to
make it right now. So, if you had no
problems with it, you might want to skip
forward. This might be a little boring,
but otherwise, I'm going to show
everyone how I would go about creating
the plate. So, uh, we need to add a new
object to the scene. We can go to the
add menu up there, or we can hit shift
A. Um, and then from this list, we want
to choose the object which most
resembles what we want to create. If you
ask me, that would be a circle. Okay, so
just like before, the bottom lefthand
corner, we can change some options here.
The biggest one being radius. It's too
big. So, drop that into about there. Um,
and you will notice that you can see
through it. Okay. And that is because
there is no face there. This is just a
string of vertices. And as I touched on
briefly earlier, vertices don't show up
in your render. Faces do. So we need to
add a type of face underneath fill. So
there's two options. Either of them will
do. Engon is just one single face shared
amongst the 32 or the triangle fan will
mean uh there's one point in the middle.
Um you can actually see it in this mode.
One point in the middle and then it just
creates um triangles to that point. I'm
going to go with engon because you know
it's never failed me [snorts] for this
option. So I'll just use that. Okay.
Now, we need to uh add more geometry to
this because we need to create some sort
of a lip for the plate. You can't just
have a plate. It's always got to have a
rim on or else that stuff slides off it,
right? So, into edit mode by hitting
tab. Um I'm to add some geometry. I'm
going to extrude. So, I'm going to hit
E. Okay. And in this state, it's now
saying, yeah, where do you want to place
it? And it's extruding it along the
normal, which is that invisible line
that faces out from the face in there.
Um and I'm just going to do a single
click right here. Um, now before we
start scaling and pulling this out,
you'll notice that obviously that's
intersecting our mesh, we need to delete
that face because we don't need it. So,
I'm going to hit X to delete. And then
what type of deletion? Not edges, not
vertices, obviously, cuz that would be,
you know, the entire line. Um, I want to
delete just the single face on top. And
there we go. So, now I can reselect that
line by holding down alt and then left
clicking on it. And now if I want to
create like a lip, which is not just
straight up, but a little bit out, I
would just scale. So S to scale. And
then just pulling my mouse out until it
looks something like that. Do a click to
confirm. Okay. And then I'm going to do
another extrusion cuz I'm going to
create like another bit like a little
bit of a flat area. Okay. So E. And then
I don't actually want to pull it
upwards. Obviously, I want to pull it
outwards. So what I do is I cancel the
movement. And now that I'm in that
state, I'm going to hit S to pull
outwards like so. Um, by the way, I
should show you as well. If after you
have like extruded something, like let's
say you do this, right? Oops. You if you
did this, if you extruded and then you
uh like cleared its position, but then
accidentally clicked off it, you've now
got double vertices all along this this
line here. And that's horrible because
it will it will create jagged artifacts
in it. So this is a really super common
problem that you will experience all the
time. And the way to fix it is to select
your entire mesh, then hit M to merge,
and then you're going to go by distance.
And you'll see in the bottom there that
little thing that says removed 32
vertices. And that has cleared up that
problem. So I have to show you that cuz
people will do it. It'll happen. And um
that's how you fix that issue. But
again, if you run into issues like this,
use my unstuck yourself guide. Link is
in the description because I did set it
up so you guys can um hopefully get
through this tutorial. All right, so as
I said, extrude, clear its like
movement, so its placement is exactly
where it started from, but then I'm
going to hit S to scale outwards. So now
I've got a little flat rim to my plate.
And then now that it's here, I'm going
to do one further extrusion upwards. And
this is just obviously the design of the
plate that I'm choosing. So upwards. Now
you can see it's like freehand like
that. I don't like it. So I'm just going
to lock it on the Z axis. So just hit Z.
So it's going straight up like so. Okay,
great. We've got a very jaggedy looking
plate that you sometimes see in video
games. You're playing Call of Duty or
something. You get up close and you go
like, "Look at that jagged old plate
there." Um, which by the way is cuz in
games the plate is like one of a million
objects and they can only put so many
polies into the scene. So little things,
little details on um tables and things
often end up a little low res. Anyways,
go to your modifier stack. Um, and the
first one we want to add to kind of
smooth this out is our very favorite
subdivision surface right where my head
is. Um, or you can access it from the
search subdivision. There we go. Okay,
cool. And I'm going to go level two. And
we've got that crimping effect happening
to the middle of our plate there. So,
just like before. And actually, let's
hide my doughut and my icing just so
that I can focus on the plate. And I'm
also going to turn off the subdiv just
so that I can select this single face
here because just like before, the
reason that's happening is it's like
right on the edge there. It has to like
convert all that into like a single
point in the middle and it's just too
ugly when it starts there. So, we just
may have to make it start way further in
the middle like that. And then when we
do that, it's clear. It's practically
invisible. You can only see it if you
get really close, but you won't see it
cuz it'll be under the donut and it'll
be smooth. Anyway, um cool. Now, um I
can tighten up the edges here cuz this
is looking very very um smooth. So, I
showed you before how you can add a loop
cut. You can do CtrlR. Okay. And that'll
add a loop cut in the middle. And then I
just pull it out towards the edge like
that to make a smoothed uh sorry a um
sharpened
uh point. Yeah. Anyway, um the other way
to do it, which I didn't talk about, but
you can do a crease. So, if we just hold
down alt and then we select that line
there, um you can do a crease. If you uh
right click, you'll see you've got there
edge crease or the hotkey shift E. So in
this when you do shift E, you'll see at
the top there you've you're pulling out
basically a value from one to zero. Um
and essentially what it's doing is it's
like doing a fake kind of tighten on
that edge there. So it's kind of like
pulling it out and just making it a
sharper point. It doesn't look as nice.
You don't get as much of a bevel because
there's no geometry being added there
like you would if you were to actually
do a loop cut. You get all this extra
geometry. So, it's not it's not as good,
but for like small things, it's, you
know, it's generally fine to do
something like that. All right, I'm
going to do a shade smooth now cuz I
want to see how that looks. And that's
pretty good. Now, the only other thing,
the exact same thing. It's weird that
like three things in this small little
scene have the exact same two modifiers,
subserve and uh solidify. Um, anyways,
generate, solidify. And just like
before, we want this solidify to go
first because otherwise it's doing it
after the fact and then we get this like
really annoying like hard line there. So
just pull that up to the top. And now
it's rounded. And look at that. Um but
yeah, I might actually want to make this
line a little bit harder. So I'll pull
that in. It's still Yeah, there's just
not enough geometry there. I This is one
of the cases where you just need more
geometry. So I'm going to add a loop cut
here. And I'll add another loop cut
underneath it. Like that. And now
I'm going to just select this. And I'm
just going to revert that edge crease.
So shift E. And then I just go like
minus one. Like so. And now it's just
Yeah, the way it was before. But there
you go. So now I've got a sharper edge
on it. The only other thing I might just
pull up this lip here. So alt select on
that lip. G Z. And I'll just pull it up
a little bit. Um, and there you go. And
we would model from reference, but I
actually had like a photo scan plate
from Polygon, which we'll get to later.
Um, but yeah, this is just modeling from
that reference that I already had, but
this is the design of it. So, there you
go. Great. Now, let's bring back our
donut and our icing. Now, I saw a
comment on the last video that said, uh,
you didn't make the donut lumpy like
last time. It's so over. Why? Oh, ye
have little faith. You think I would
forget something like that?
Maybe I did forget, [laughter]
but I'm actually glad I did because this
is a great opportunity to talk about a
new tool. So, for those that haven't
watched a previous version, before we
did the icing, um, we made the donut
lumpy, which I did by going into edit
mode and then I just selected vertices
using proportional editing and like, you
know, like pul pulled it out, right? And
just kind of like maybe I shrink some
parts in this kind of thing. And the
reason this is important is that this
adds natural variation because you know
you could have scientists working for a
thousand years in a lab and they would
never be able to create a donor as
perfectly mathematically accurate as our
3D software has done. This is too
perfect. there is natural variation and
we need to see that for the eye to go
this is you know a real you know uh
something realistic right and it's hard
to do this kind of thing after you've
already added the donut sorry the icing
because you can see it just has no
bearing on the icing over the top right
so some things in 3D are easier to do
earlier than they are to do later and
this is something you just learn as you
do 3D like you'll you'll do so many
projects where you just like you get to
the end and you go like oh man why
didn't I do that before I did this now
this is
I've like 3xed the amount of work and
you just learn these things over time.
However, there are certain tools um and
there is one I'm going to introduce you
to in a second that enable you to make
these sort of changes after. Um by the
way, there is a way like you can select
both objects like this um which you you
that is something that you can do in
Blender now. You didn't used to always
be able to, but you can now edit both
objects together. So, I could do this.
It does have like a clipping issue when
you try to do like shrink fatten, but
you can get some like natural lumpy
variations going this way. Um, and you
can do that. That's actually fine. But I
do want to introduce you to a new tool
that is in 5.0. Um, and it is if you
select both of your icing and your
doughut together, then you hit shift A
and then you go lattice. There's a new
option for lattice deform selected. We
always had lattice, but it was very
finicky to set up. But now you've got
lattice deform selected. And that adds
this what looks like a cube, like a
bounding box over your object. Um, but
it's not actually going to appear in
your render. All it is is a defamation
guide. So if you just select these
points, you can see we are twisting the
donut. But importantly, the actual donut
is underneath. Like this is a modifier,
right? So we're not actually changing
the mesh at all. It's just doing this
after the fact. And then if I just
deleted my lattice, like it's it's gone.
It's back to where it was. So this is a
non-destructive workflow. These these
little points here, they enable me to at
any point in the future change and
deform a mesh, which is actually really
useful. And it's because you're not
often in this the uh the exact
circumstance where you know exactly what
you're going to do and then at the end
of it like you know the order in which
to do things. Sometimes you're working
with a client and they've got an idea
for something and then far later on
they're like, you know what, let's
change the proportions of the car or
whatever it is and you have to be able
to like fix it without redoing all your
mesh. So that's what a lattis can do.
Now it comes by default with just this
low res cube over it. But if down here
you click this little uh data property
uh for the lattice, you've got
resolution here. So I can increase this.
I can add in some more resolution here.
And importantly, I want to add one in
the middle here. Um, because the first
thing you notice when you look at
reference of donuts, um, is that besides
the the lumpy shape, the bit around the
middle of the doughut is often whiter
and it's not as puffy. And when you look
at how donuts are cooked, it's actually
easy to see why. It's it's half
submerged in the oil and then it is
flipped over onto the other side and
then the other side cooks. So, it cooks
one side and then it cooks the other.
and the bits uh sorry near the surface
of the oil that's the the uh the oil is
less hot, right? Because it's near the
surface, so it's escaping. So that oil
is less hot. The oil that's underneath
it is much hotter and then it flips it
over. And so again, you always have this
bit around the middle that just isn't
quite cooked as well as the other stuff.
So it ends up being a little bit
lighter. It's also less puffy. So no
doughut actually comes out at that
perfectly round shape. It's usually
always kind of almost concave actually
around the middle. So with this, I can
select all of these points here like so.
I have to shift select them. I can't do
the alt click around it cuz it's not
technically a mesh. Um, and then I can
just scale it in like uh turn off
proportional editing if you've got it
on. And then just shrink it in like
that. And that by itself will add just a
little bit of realism to this cuz that
is a detail that your eye won't notice.
Everyone thinks donuts are just, you
know, they're perfectly round, but
they're actually not, right? They're
always got this like concave kind of
shape around it. So, that will add uh
some realism, but then I can add in some
little areas here where one part it got
a little bit more puffy on that side, so
that part's a little bit raised up. Um,
and obviously this isn't as detailed as
if you had, you know, if you were
manipulating the the Taurus underneath,
right? I can't do like, you know, small
details. I can't, you know, sculpt in an
area or do or do some crazy changes, but
it's enough in in a pinch to do
something like this. I'm just going to
hide my plate. Um, which by the way, you
can do it by hitting the eyropper, which
is what I've been doing up there. So,
not the eyropper, the eye icon. Um, you
can also, um, do it by hitting H. So,
you select an object in the viewport,
you hit H, and then you hit Alt H to
bring it back. So H or alt H um is a
good hotkey to remember. [snorts] Um and
then here, so at the bottom here, cuz
yeah, the same thing will happen at the
bottom. There'll be parts where like the
donut looks a little bit like raised on
the plate a little bit like this. Just
around the middle here.
Um
like that.
There you go. Something like that. But
this is just just a small amount of
defamation, right? It might seem
unnecessary, but it does help. It really
does help things to feel more realistic
when you go to the trouble of doing some
of this. Um, and it's super super
important. Um, but we can also now apply
it once I know that I like everything. I
don't want to have this like lattice
sitting over it forever. So, I can just
apply that by going to uh apply and then
selecting the donut. And I can also say
apply there. Um, and now I can just
delete this lattice. And now it's like I
modeled that, right? All those shapes
are now like baked into it. Um, and it
looks good. As I said before, if you did
want to do any more detail, you could,
you know, shift select multiple objects,
go into edit mode. Um, and then using
proportional editing, you could also do
some like more targeted tweaks. If you
really wanted to, uh, you know,
manipulate the donut, you could do that.
So, there are things that you can do.
Um, it does make a difference. it is
important. Um, but you know, it is also
optional, but it's it's an excuse to
kind of introduce you to some more tools
and things in Blender. So, I'm kind of
glad that I uh didn't do it at the start
because um we can introduce you to that
that kind of thing. So, all right, we
got a lumpy looking donut. Good for us.
Now, now is the exciting bit. We can
talk about rendering.
Making this actually look good because
this is gray. This is boring. This is
called the 3D viewport view. Okay. The
the reason this looks looks boring and
flat is that this is cheaper for your
computer to actually process just the
shapes in like a gray. There's no
shadows. There's no lighting. There's no
surface interaction or anything like
that. This is fast for your computer to
see to create that pretty image that
looks realistic with light calculations
and everything. That is called a render.
And you can do a render by either
hitting F12 on your keyboard or by going
to render and then saying render image.
Huh. And now that has taken a snapshot.
The problem is is it looks like not the
view that we were looking at. So we're
looking at this view. Why did we get a
view up here? The reason is is that
Blender will always take the render from
the camera view. So remember that thing
that's like way out in the middle of
nowhere we haven't touched. It's taking
the view from that that camera. And you
can look through the camera by hitting
the camera view icon over there.
[snorts] So now that I'm here in this
view, um, how do we move it in close?
How do we get it close to our thing? So
there's there's a number of like
traditional ways to bring a camera into
like in Blender. I'll actually show you
the way I first learned to do this cuz
it's actually just like natural to me.
Um, but then I'll show you the method
that actually most people prefer. So you
can just with the camera selected, you
can hit G. You can move things around
like that. If you want to bring it in
like just zoom to the like
straightforward if you hit G and then
middle mouse button that will like kind
of what's it called? Dolly dolly in and
out which can be uh very useful. Um and
then if I want to like tilt it um I can
like just hit rotate like that or I can
rotate along the Z axis, right? Cuz I
know how to like turn the camera. So,
that was how I learned to use uh the
camera and how a lot of people still
like to do it. But a lot of new people
prefer this because now in 5.0, it's
actually just a button right here. If
you click this button now, I can use the
same controls that I used before um to
to move the camera. Because if you don't
have that checked, the moment you just
like hit your middle mouse to like orbit
somewhere else, it leaves the camera
behind. Okay. But when you have when
you're looking through the camera and
you have this checked now, when I orbit
around and I zoom and I do all the same
controls as before, shift middle mouse,
I can position the camera exactly where
I want it. Get it right there um without
having to worry. You just have to
remember, don't then immediately orbit
like you're going to go do something cuz
the camera is still locked to your view.
So, you have to make sure you uncheck it
when you're done and then the camera is
locked to that position there. Um, and
by the way, this is like a small thing,
but when you're working with like small
objects, you often have to like change
because Blender is like designed for
like environment like like like big
types of scenes. This this camera is
just too big. So, if you go to the
camera settings, click the camera thing,
then go to viewport display. I just
changed the display of this. This has no
bearing on the actual like final render.
This is just how it displays in your
viewport so that it's not so gigantic
it's taking over everything. All right,
the other way you can quickly look
through the camera is numpad zero. So
numpad zero will take you in and out.
All right, but now that I'm there, I can
hit F12 and look at that. That is a
different look. It It's still gray
because the default materials are gray.
Um, but you can see there is shadow
there. But check this out. We can do
even more. So besides just shadow, like
you might notice looking, by the way,
you can bring back a render by hitting
F11. Uh, I should also mention, by the
way, the first time you do a render, um,
I think the first time, like, if you've
just opened Blender for the first time
and you hit render, it'll have to do a
bunch of like shader compilations and
stuff like that, it should only need to
do that once. It shouldn't have to do it
every time you open Blender. We're using
EV, which is a rendering engine we'll
talk about soon. Um, but this there is
some of that. Every time you you render,
like to when you create a new shader, it
has to like develop those things. But
anyways, it should it the first time it
should be slow, but it should be quicker
for every render after that. Okay, so
there's shadow here, but you'll notice
like in here there's no there's no
detail whereas in the real world you
would see like bounce lighting from the
the end of the plate there. You would
see like some crevice information. Um
there would be it' be darker and things
and that is because by default there's
an option that is turned off. So if you
go to your render properties at the top
there, this has all the information just
pertaining to how something is going to
be rendered. And by default, ray tracing
is turned off, which I think is a
mistake. I think they should change it
to default on because so many people
don't like EV, this rendering engine,
because they they think it just produces
fake looking images. But when you turn
on ray tracing, look at how much better
that looks. Um, by the way, if you want
to compare renders, you can change to a
new slot and then uh you can do a
render, another render, and then you've
got the previous render and then uh the
new render in slot two. And then you can
flip back by hitting J on your keyboard.
And that's a way you can like quickly
compare settings, which is very useful.
Um, but you can see with ray tracing
turned on, this is off. Turned on, we
get bounce lighting. So there's some
light that's hitting the plate there and
it's bouncing up. We've got like more
information in the crevices. Um, and it
just looks a lot more realistic than it
did before. Um, you'll also have
reflections when I show you some uh
material properties. So, that is
something you should have on all the
time when you're using um EV. By the
way, there is another rendering engine
called Cycles, and it is much more
realistic. However, it is a lot more
slower. Um, it's honestly I I'm going to
show you at the end a comparison between
Cycles and EV, but it's actually
negligible if you know the right
settings for EV. So, I'm going to keep
it on Eevee for the rest, which is
actually good because Eevee is actually
pretty powerful at doing most things.
It's just it's it's a game engine style,
so it's it's a rasterized rendering
engine, whereas uh Cycles is a path
trace rendering engine. Much more
computationally heavy. Um whereas uh EV
is much more faster. So, we're going to
keep it on EV and I'm going to show you
how to get really great results with it.
And then at the end, we're going to flip
it to cycles. So, if you want to see
that final result, you can get it. But
we're not going to start there because
it's just not necessary and I don't
think most people will actually need it.
Okay. So, I'm going to talk about some
materials. But first, um you'll notice
like it's kind of annoying to have to
like render something like go to render
it every time you want to see um an
image like that. And thankfully, you
don't have to because in the top view
here, these little icons, there is a
mode here called render view mode. And
this puts the render in real time. Look
at that. I don't have to hit the render
to wait to see my result. I can see it
in my viewport. So, it used to be that
like rendering engines were so slow that
really to do a render was like a big
task. You hit render and it would take
hours to process something and it didn't
look anything as good as this, right?
But now rendering is like and computers
are so fast that we can just have
rendering running constantly whilst we
are working and it's usually not
computationally heavy. Um so this is
yeah this is Eevee which is the the much
faster one. um cycles would be a little
slower, but still. Anyways, now that
we're in render view mode, let's talk
about materials. So, let's start with
the like most different material. Let's
go with the icing. So, looking at our
icing here, if I want to make this look
pink and change its overall appearance,
if I go down to my material panel down
here or material properties, um and then
I can just click on new material. And
now I've got a bunch of different
options here. Okay. And these all do
different things for um for for the the
surface appearance. Like metallic will
make it look like metal, right? Uh
roughness will change like how sharp the
reflection looks. Uh the base color,
this is like the main one you want to
change for almost every object. This is
just the base color of the object. So
obviously I can make that look pink like
that. Let's pull in here a little bit
closer. Focus on that. Um so I can make
it look nice and pink. Uh, the other
thing is is it's looking like way too
diffused. It's almost like a chalk
looking icing. But if I bring this back,
I can make this look more shiny. I don't
want to go like too far cuz then it's
like mirror reflection. I want to go
like, you know, somewhere around 2. The
great thing is is we can really change
these values at any point in the future.
So when we add in other objects and
there's different lighting setups, some
of the settings can look a little off at
that point. Um, so it's very very common
to like once you've set up all your
lighting and everything to like
re-evaluate your materials, but this
completely non-destructive. I can change
these at any time. And now I could
create some very simple materials. Like
I could say, let's make this look black.
Make it like a black shiny glossy
ceramic mug. So, um, by the way, you'll
notice I'm not going all the way to
black. There's a kind of a unspoken
Well, it's not unspoken. People speak
it. um you shouldn't um uh go fully
black or fully white or like same with
like uh colors. You shouldn't go like
100% saturation on a color because
things start to clip. It's maybe a
little outdated as like now color
management is getting so good it's it
knows actually how to handle saturated
stuff and like dark things, but it's
still like a general rule. Um, you never
want to go like fully black because
things are never truly like the real
black is vant black, right? Which
[snorts] is like just this material
which is like scientifically created to
like emit no uh reflection simplifying
it. But yeah, so like things will even a
black mug that looks really black to you
is probably not entirely black. So it's
still there's going to be a little bit
of lightness to it. So I'm just adding
that in there. Uh the roughness. This is
where I can make this. If I wanted this
to look like a, you know, shiny ceramic
mug, I could do something like that.
These are just placeholders, by the way.
I'm just using this as an example of how
to create very simple um materials. Uh
the plate here, uh let's go. Yeah, make
it just look a little bit shinier than
by itself. And then the donut, let's go
give it a, you know, brownish lightish
color like that. Make it a little bit
darker like so. Um, another value which
is super important for something like
icing and and uh the donut and it's it's
really important for just two things
which is food and characters and it is
that um when light hits objects like
this they are mushy right they're made
of like organic matter and so light
actually enters the object and it kind
of scatters around inside it and then it
re-exits it. Um, it's the reason why
when you like look at your hand in front
of a light or the sun or something, you
can see the light shining through. You
can even see your bones through your
hand if it's a bright enough light. Um,
so it's called subsurface scattering.
And that value is underneath here where
it says subsurface. If you go down here,
um, you want to turn the weight all the
way up to one cuz this is not the
intensity of it. This is just like
apparently this value is supposed to be
zero or one. It shouldn't be somewhere
in between. to control how much of it is
the scale which is how much how far into
the surface will the light penetrate. Um
and then you can see here you can
increase this or decrease this and you
can see the light kind of get into it.
Now by default it looks red which I also
think is a mistake. Um it's very
suitable for characters because
characters need red cuz inside a
character is blood right but for every
other thing like food it shouldn't be
red. Um, and confusingly and and I know
there's a mathematical reason for this
because of like how light in the physics
of things, but like different
wavelengths travel at different speeds
right inside the surf. That's how I
understand it. So they've they've made
the color of the subsurface
um
RG and B separated here. So you can see
we've got red as one, then we've got
green as 2, and then blue as 0.1. So
essentially, I need to clear all those
out and make them one, which here's a
tip. You can drag over multiple values
in Blender. So if you just click and
drag down across something, and then you
can just type in one and then hit enter
and it makes all of those one. Um, and
then now I can, you know, tweak this. I
can make this look a little bit more
milky like that. But we can, you know,
we can adjust those. I'll do the same
thing for my donut here. Um, give it
some subsurface. Turn that up. And then
I'll set this to one. And then, yeah,
let's just leave it at the default
value. But you can see that that's with
subsurface on. Actually, let me bring
the camera in. All right. I'm going to
go lock it. Bring this in. And I'm going
to do a before and after render. So,
this is how you can use these these
slots. So, this is with subsurface on.
Then I'll go to slot two. And now I'm
going to select this. And I'll turn it
off. And then I'll do another render.
And now hit J back and forth. So, that's
the difference that subsurface can make
to something. You can see here where
it's like fully dark. It's actually now
the light is passing through it and
that's what gives something a milky kind
of look. Um, and it's, as I said, it's
it's mostly true for things like food.
You can see it. I take photos of it
myself all the time when I'm out and
about cuz I'm like, "Look at that
subsurface." And my family think I'm
weird. Um, but I I think it's cool. So,
anyways, there you go. So, that's that
subsurface. All right. Um, I'm gonna
pull the camera out to here and then um
let's add a table because this has to be
a table. Uh we're going to do the
texturing in the next part. Um but let's
add a table. Now, normally if it was a
table that you were um Make sure I turn
that off while I while I orbit around.
You know, if this was a large scene,
right, uh whatever, you would have to do
like model an actual table. If you know
the camera is only going to be here,
doesn't matter about anything except the
top surface. So, all we need to model is
shift a plane. That's it. That's our
table. I I just have to scale it up a
little bit. But this is our table. It's
actually really common in 3D if you look
at like breakdowns of 3D scenes in
movies and stuff. Everything is fakery.
They just like buildings are cards. They
just like a a plane with a texture
slapped on it. Nothing is real. Um you
know, when the camera moves, they might
have to like model things properly and
people go like, "Oh, I have to model it
now." Um but like if the camera's here,
it doesn't matter. Just make it a plane.
Um there you go. So, that's that's a a
donut on a plate with a mug. And that
for somebody who has never used 3D
before, that's an achievement. Um, this
is the kind of thing that like back in
the '90s, you probably would have won
like scholarships for and stuff if you
could pull this off. This used to be
insanely difficult. It is still pretty
difficult cuz 3D is hard. Um, but yeah,
if you have uh uh if you're new at it,
this should make you proud. You you've
pulled this off. If you want to save
this, by the way, you can go image and
then go save. Um, and then you can just
save an image, PNG. You got all the
options, JPEG, etc. Um, however, if you
want to make this look good, in the next
parts, we're going to be making this
look much, much better by doing some
texturing and making our table look good
and adding some ceramic textures and
things to different objects. But this is
kind of the end of the modeling section
of the doughut tutorial. Um so we we
touched on you know basic primitives. We
add slight defamations. Um we extruded
some things to uh create like an organic
looking shape. Did a little bit of
sculpting. Um and then we created a mug
right and then did some uh modifiers and
subsurf to kind of uh create the general
shape there. So those are kind of some
of the techniques that you will need to
learn to create lots of different
objects in the future. Just some though.
But there are so many other techniques
and tools. Uh precision modeling,
modeling mostly with hard objects, how
to keep straight lines and then modeling
something that is really custom and
deformed. Getting those like largeish
shapes there and just kind of like
almost using the mesh like a guide mesh
to kind of uh create shapes. And then
actual characters like sculpting a
character from nothing and then actually
converting that character into something
that looks and has like like subdivision
so that the arm can move and then
rigging that character so that you can
actually move the arms like a puppet. So
these are the kinds of techniques that
we don't have time to go into in the
donut but I do have time to go into in
my course called the beginners academy.
So all of these things you can see on
the screen here are taught in that
academy. If you only want to learn
Blender for free and you just want to do
this donut, that is fine. But if you
want to go further and you want to learn
how to actually think like a 3D artist
and take an idea from your head and
actually convert that into something
that you can use, whether that be for 3D
printing or for rendering or for
whatever visualization purpose you have.
Um, that's what this course is about.
It's teaching you those foundational
skills um to actually um create
something that you want to create. So,
if you're interested in that, uh the
link for that is uh beneath this video
and um it is designed for complete
beginners who have finished the donut.
But you've learned enough now that if
you want to jump straight to that, you
could. But if you want to continue on,
we will jump into texturing next. I will
see you in the next